ANS Record Group 1: Administrative, 1853-ongoing
American Numismatic Society
- Series: General correspondence, 1853 - 2099; 133 cubic feet
  - Box 9.9.1 A-I (1942)
    Applicants.; American District Telegraph Company.; Addressograph.; American Council of Learned Societies.; A.; B.; C.; Clapp, George; Council.; D.; E.; F.; G.; Gillingham.; Gift acknowledgements.; H.; I.
  - Box 9.9.2 J-Z (1942)
    J; K; L; M; Milbank, Samuel R.; N; O; P; Pond, Shepard; Q; R; S; T; U; V; W; XYZ.
  - Box 10.1.1 A-P (1943)
    Addressograph.; American Council of Learned Societies.; American District Telegraph Company.; Applicants.; A.; B.; Central Hanover Bank.; Council.; C.; D.; E.; F.; Gift acknowledgements.; Gillingham, Harrold.; G.; H.; I.; J.; K.; L.; Milbank, Samuel.; M.; Noe, Sydney.; N.; O.; Pond, Shepard.; Publicity.
  - Box 10.1.2 Q-Z (1943)
    Q.; R.; S.; Sigler.; S.; T.; U.; V.; W.
  - Box 10.2.1 A-F (1944)
    Addresses.; Addressograph.; Applicants.; A.; B.; Clapp.; Central Hanover Bank.; Council.; C.; D.; Exhibition, 1943-44.; E.; F.
  - Box 10.2.2 G-Z (1944)
    Gift acknowledgements.; Gillingham, Harrold.; G.; H.; I.; J.; K.; L.; Mac/Mc.; M.; Newell Committee.; Noe, Sydney.; N.; O.; Pond, Shepard.; Publicity.; P.; Q.; R.; S.; T.; U.; V.; West, Louis C.; W.; X-Z.
  - Box 10.3.1 A-N (1945)
    Bullowa.; Bullowa.; B.; Dewing.; D.; D.; D.; E.; Gillingham.; Grant.; G.; Huntington.; H.; I.; J.
  - Box 10.3.2 O-Z (1945)
    Numismatic Notes and Monographs.; Office supplies.; O.; Pond, Shepard.; Powills, M.A.; Publication Committee.; P.; Q.; R.; Supplemental folder on stencils.; S.; T.; U.; Vermilya-Brown.; V.; W.; X-Z.
  - Box 10.4.1 A-N (1946)
    Acknowledgements.; American Council of Learned Societies.; A.; Baldwin.; Bellinger.; Blackwell.; Bluestone.; Bolender.; Bourgey.; Baldwin-Brett, Agnes.; B.; B.; Casa Pardo.; Ciani.; Clapp.; Clarke, T.J.; C.; Davenport.; Dewing.; Douglas.; D.; D.; Eklund.; E.; E.; Feuardent.; Florange.; F.; F.; Gettys.; Geunther, Paul.; Gillingham, Harrold.; Glendining.; G.; G.; Hostetler.; H.; H.; International Antiquariaat.; I.; I.; Jorgensen.; J.; J.; K.; K.; Leroux, Ernest.; Le Soudier.; Luzac.; L.; Mac/Mc.; Mc.; Medallic Art Company.; Mehl, Max.; Milne, J.G.; Mosher, S.; Munzen and Medaillen.; M.; M.; Nardecchia, Libreria Gia.; Newell, E.T. (Mrs.).; Noe, Sydney.; N.; N.
  - Box 10.4.2 O-Z (1946)
    Office Des Editions Francaises.; Oxford University Press.; O.; O.; Pond, Shepard.; Pagani, A.; Page, Alfred.; Platt, Clement.; Pond, Shepard.; Pradeau.; Probsthain.; P.; P.; Quaritch, B.; Q.; Q.; Ratto.; Raymond, Wayte.; Reagan, Lewis M.; Risk.; Roberts, John T.; R.; R.; Sanders.; Santamaria.; Santos Leitao.; Schwabacher, W.; Simpson, A.C.; Spink.; S.; S.; Tinchant, P.; U.; U.; V.; V.; W.; W.; West, Louis.; X-Z.
  - Box 10.5.2 A-H (1947)
    Acknowledgements.; Addressograph.; American Council of Learned Societies.; American Council of Learned Societies.; American Council of Learned Societies.; A.; A.; Baldwin.; Bell, Harold.; Bellinger.; Bellinger.; Brett.; Bullowa.; Burzio.; B.; Clapp.; Clarke, T.J.; C.; Dewing.; de Terreros, M. Romero.; Douglas.; E.; Ecklund.; E.; F.; Gettys.; Gillingham, Harrold.; Guerassimoff, T.; Guild, William.; G.; Hosteller.; Huntington, Archer M.; H.
  - Box 10.6.1 I-Z (1947)
    Intelligencer.; International Antiquariaat.; I.; Jorgensen.; J.; K.; L.; Mc.; Maiuri, Amadeo. Medallic Art Company.; Meritt, B.D.; Merrymount Press.; Merrymount Press.; Merrymount Press.; Milne, J.G.; Mosher, S. M.; Newell, Edward (Mrs.).; Noe, Sydney P.; N.; O.; Pond, Shepard (Mrs.).; Pradeau.; Publication Committee.; P.; Raymond, Wayte.; Regan, Louis M.; Risk.; Robert, L.; Roberts, John T.; R.; Q.; Santamaria.; Simpson, A.C.; Sutherland, C.H.V.; S.; T.; U.; Vermilia-Brown.; V.; West, Louis.; W.; Y.; Z.; A.; B.; C.; D.; E.; F.; G.; H.; I.; J.; K.; L.; M.; N.; O.; P.; Q.; R.; S.; T.; U.; V.; W.; X-Z.
  - Box 10.6.2 A-K (1948)
    Acknowledgements.; Addressograph.; American Council of Learned Societies.; A.; Bellinger.; Bullowa.; B.; Clapp.; Clarke, T. James.; C.; Dewing.; E.; Fecht estate.; Fraleigh, W.N.; F.; Gillingham.; Guild, William.; G.; Huntington.; India – dealers; I.
  - Box 10.7.1 L-Z (1948)
    L.; Mc.; Milne.; M.; Noe, Sydney P.; N.; Pond, Shepard (Mrs.).; P.; Raymond, Wayte.; Reagan, Lewis.; Risk.; Roberts, John.; R.; Simpson, A.C.; S.; T.; U.; V.; Vermilya-Brown.; W.; Y.; Z.; A.; B.; C.; D.; E.; F.; G.; H.; I.; J.; K.; L.; M.; N.; O.; P.; Q.; R.; S.; T.; U.; V.; W.; X-Z
  - Box 10.7.2 A-M (1949)
    Acknowledgements.; American Council of Learned Societies.; Bullowa, D.M.; Clarke, T. James.; Dewing.; D.; E.; F.; Fraleigh, William N.; Frye.; Gillingham.; G.; Hill.; Huntington.; H.; India - dealers.; I.; J.; K.; L.; Mailer's.; Merrymount Press.; Milbank.; M.
  - Box 10.8.1 M-Z (1949)
  - Box 10.8.2 A-J (1950)
  - Box 10.9.1 K-Z (1950)
    K.; L.; McGregor and Werner.; Mc.; Mailer's.; Milbank.; M.; Nash, Chauncey.; N.; O.; P.; Q.; Raymond.; Roberts.; R.; Simpson.; Spink & Son.; Stewart, James R.; T.; U.; V.; West.; W.; A.; B.; C.; D.; E.; F.; G.; H.; I.; J.; K.; L.; M.; N.; O.; P.; Q.; R.; S.; T.; U.; V.; X-Z.
  - Box 10.9.2 A-Q (1951)
    A.; Accra.; Bullowa.; DeNise, D. (Mrs.).; E.; F.; Gautier.; G.; H.; I.; J.; K.; L.; Mc.; Mailer's.; Milbank.; M.; N.; O.; P.; Q.
  - Box 11.1.1 (R-Z) (1951)
    Roberts, John.; Seltman, C.; S.; T.; U.; V.; W.; West, Louis C.; X-Z.; A.; B.; C.; D.; E.; F.; G.; H.; I.; J.; K.; L.; M.; N.; O.; P.; Q.; R.; S.; T.; U.; V.; W.; X-Z.
  - Box 11.1.2 A-T (1952)
    Acknowledgements.; American Museum of Natural History.; A.; B.; C.; CARE.; D.; E.; F.; H.; I.; J.; K.; L.; M.; Mc.; Milbank, Samuel.; N.; Noe, Sydney.; O.; P.; Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts.; Q.; R.; S.; T.
  - Box 11.2.1 U-Z (1952)
    U.; UNESCO.; W.; West, Louis C.; V.; X-Z.; A.; B.; C.; D.; E.; F.; G.; H.; I.; J.; K.; L.; M.; N.; O.; P.; Q.; R.; S.; T.; U.; V.; W.; X-Z.
  - Box 11.2.2 S-Z (1953)
    S.; T.; U.; V.; W.; West, Louis C.; X-Z.; A.; B.; C.; D.; E.; F.; G.; H.; I.; J.; K.; L.; Mc.; M.; N.; O.; P.; Q.; R.; S.; T.; U.; V.; W.; X-Z.
  - Box 11.3.1 A-S (1953)
    A.; B.; C.; Cancio, Leopoldo; D.; Dewey, Arthur to Louis West regarding Adra Newell; E.; F.; G.; H.; Huntington, Archer M.; I.; Ives, Herbert.; J.; K.; L.; Mc.; M.; Milbank, Samuel.; N.; Noe, Sydney.; O.; P.; Q.; R.; Simpson, A. Carson.
  - Box 11.3.2 A-R (1954)
    A.; B.; C.; D.; E.; F.; L.S. Forrer, Ltd.; G.; Ganz, Edward.; H.; Huntington, Archer M.; I.; Ives, Herbert.; J.; K.; L.; M.; Mc.; Milbank, Samuel.; Miles, George C.; N.; O.; P.; Q.; R.; S.
  - Box 11.4.1 R-Z (1954)
    B.A. Seaby, Ltd.; Spink & Son, Ltd.; P&P Santamaria.; Simpson, A. Carson.; Schulman, Hans.; T.; U.; V.; West, Louis C.; W.; X-Z.; A.; B.; C.; D.; E.; F.; G.; H.; I.; J.; K.; L.; M.; N.; O.; P.; Q.; R.; S.; T.; U.; V.; W.; X-Z.
  - Box 11.4.2 A-N (1955)
    A.; Ba-Bh.; Bi-Bz.; Bullowa, C.E.; C.; D.; E.; F.; L.S. Forrer, Ltd.; Gans.; G.; Gitelson.; Huntington, Archer M.; H.; I.; India.; J.; K.; L.; M.; Mc.; Milbank, Samuel.; N.
  - Box 11.5.1 O-Z (1955)
    O.; P.; Q.; R.; P&P Santamaria.; Schulman, Hans.; Simpson, A. Carson.; B.A. Seaby, Ltd.; Spink & Son.; T.; U.; V.; West, Louis C.; W.; X-Z.; A.; B.; C.; D.; E.; F.; G.; H.; I.; J.; K.; L.; M.; N.; O.; P.; Q.; R.; S.; T.; U.; V.; W.; X-Z.
- Series: Scrapbooks, 1858 - 1929; 7 scrapbooks
  Scrapbooks; Clippings (Information artifacts); Fliers (Printed matter); Circulars (Fliers); Landon, Melville D. (Melville De Lancey), 1839-1910; Saltus, J. Sanford, 1853-1922; Admission tickets
  Seven scrapbooks that appear to have been assembled and kept by an officer or administrator of the Society.
  Scrapbook 1, 1858-1902: Contains newspaper clippings on topics such as Society meeting announcements, including its first meeting in the home of Augustus B. Sage; newly proposed U.S. coinage such as the Indian Head cent; the collections of Lyman H. Low, R. Hobart Smith, Henry Russell Drowne, and James Oliver; the Central Park obelisk (Cleopatra’s Needle), Henry H. Gorringe, and Gaston L. Feuardent; medals of Christopher Columbus, Ulysses S. Grant, and Prince Henry; the Paris Exposition of 1900; William Raymond Weeks; and statements of business (coinage and deposits) from mints and assay office. Also includes a pasted in front page of the circular for the Prince Henry Medal (1902); two loose sheets from the New-York Daily Tribune with the articles “The Currency,” (September 4, 1867) and “The Obelisk’s Corner Stone” (October 10, 1880). Also includes an embossed foil seal of the Society and other examples of the seal; an embossed foil seal of the Madeleine Consolidated Mining & Milling Co. (Colorado); a ticket for the presentation of a medal to Cyrus W. Field (1861); and a blue ribbon having to do with the Grant medal with “April 23rd, 1897” on it.
  Scrapbook 2, 1864-1915: Clippings and pages from publications on topics relating to the Society such as meetings, Grant medal, Columbus medal, the Society’s exhibition of medals coinciding with World’s Columbian Exhibition (1893) and at the Paris Exposition (1900), the purchase of coins of the British Museum put on display at the Lotus Club and Boston Art Club, a lecture on Royal Egyptian jewelry by Henry de Morgan, the Society’s move to Audubon Terrace, the establishment of the School for Coin and Medal Designing and Die Cutting (1901), a “History of Presidential Medals,” by Gustav Kobbé (Sunday Magazine, October 16, 1904), new coinage designs (1907), the Daniel Parish Jr. donation, the International Exhibition of Medallic Art (1910), a large number of articles on the Joan of Arc exhibition and statue (1913), U.S. and Colonial coins exhibition (1914), Mexican coin exhibition (1914), a 31-pound Swedish coin (1914), coins and medals of warring nations exhibition (1914-1915), peace medals (1915), and the collections of Robert Hewitt Jr., William Poillon, J. Pierpont Morgan, and other members. Also, death notices or obituaries for Woodbury Gersdorf Langdon, Walter B. Lawrence, Robert Hewitt, William F. Havemeyer, J.M. Ceballos, Theodore Low De Vinne, James Buchanan Nies, and others.
  Scrapbook 3, 1914-1915: Contains clippings on numismatics generally and on the activities of various numismatic organizations, many from a clipping service. Topics include Archer M. Huntington’s gifts for the development of Audubon Terrace; Joseph C. Mitchelson’s gift of his collection to the state of Connecticut; the theft of coins from Waldo Newcomer; Huntington and his wife being arrested as spies; a full page on John Flanagan, sculptor; and various death notices or obituaries for individuals such as Jonas Coolidge Hills, J. Madison Drake, Richard A. Canfield, John Hull, Temple Bowdoin, Charles Allis, Winfred Robert Martin, William Theophilus Rogers Marvin, George Moore Smith, Charles T. Wills, Isaac E. Gates, Foster Ely, Charles J.H. Woodbury. Also found are “New Currency,” by the humorist Eli Perkins “Melville Landon,” with images of “money for lady crusaders” and “money for burglars,” among others; a facsimile of the new United States four per cent bond; a flier on the death of Edward Cogan; and a photograph of S. Hudson Chapman from a publication. Also includes long articles on New York State historic sites such as Fort Ontario, Sleepy Hollow and the capture of John Andre, and Fort Ticonderoga, which was owned by Society member William Pell.
  Scrapbook 4, 1894-1929: Contains clippings and pages from publications, mostly having to do with military medals, medals of honor, insignia, foreign orders, and royalty, all reflecting the interests of Society member J. Sanford Saltus who wrote some of the notes accompanying the clippings. Also includes some items of general interest regarding the Society, such as death notices or obituaries for William Poillon, James T. Pyle, Asher D. Atkinson, Louis Comparette, Samuel Hudson Chapman, and Baumann Lowe Belden. There is a folder of loose clippings with related materials, such as death notices for Robert C. Ogden and William R. Powell.
  Scrapbook 5, 1867-1925: Contains printed circulars (cards and sheets) announcing ANS meetings and programs.
  Scrapbook 6, 1859-1877: Contains newspaper clippings; informational flyers and advertisements; price lists; photos and photo engravings of both coins and medals; and articles about socio-economic issues relating to money. Handwritten at the back of the last leaf: “Pages – sixty-three leaves text twenty-nine leaves blank – no leaves missing. Bound volume collated Nov. 6, 1914” Highlights include: Article by Charles Dickens in “Current Coin” (1876); “American Journal of Numismatics and Bulletin of the American Numismatic and Archeological Societies”, vol. IV, no. 5 (1869); numerous articles and advertisements concerning the business of Edward Cogan including a pointed letter of retort from Cogan (Feb. 2, 1869) to Mason & Company concerning their sale of the Randall collection in which Cogan vehemently defends his integrity; price list published by medalist John W. Kline describing medals of famous Americans; numerous newspaper articles dealing with coin discoveries and counterfeiting including an article (with picture) describing a counterfeit coin detector (1877); advertisements for the sales of Washington centennial medals and centennial medals of 1876. Also includes newspaper articles dealing with the history of metal coinage and paper money; the San Francisco coining press; articles on ancient methods of coining from “The Practical Mechanic’s Journal” (10/1/1868); material from Frank Leslie’s Illustrated Newspaper (Apr. 10, 1875) describing a gold medal of France created as a tribute to the abolitionist John Brown. And also includes an interesting article from the New York Sun (Feb. 26, 1877) discussing President Grant’s last Sunday in the Executive Mansion; and a mock advertisement, with pictures, for satirical currency created by humorist Melville D. Landon, AKA “Eli Perkins” (1839-1910).
  Scrapbook 7, 1906, 1907: With only eleven pages, scrapbook contains newspaper articles mostly collected in 1906 and some few articles from 1907. The cover of the scrapbook has affixed the book template of the American Numismatic and Archeological Society (ANAS). Material consists of newspaper articles, photographs, and announcements of numismatic-related events, including commemorative medals authorized by the ANAS celebrating famous Americans. The newspapers represented include: New York Sun, New York Herald, Evening Post, and many smaller circulation newspapers from New York and other states. Many articles were provided by the Manhattan Press Clipping Bureau which had offices in New York, Paris, and London. Highlights include: ANAS announcement for the unveiling of Ulysses S. Grant’s tomb and the commemorative medal commissioned by ANAS for striking and designed by Tiffany & Co. (1897). ANAS announcement of a plaque commemorating John Paul Jones, designed by medalist Victor D. Brenner (1906). Articles announcing (for the time) high prices paid for various coins; articles explaining the coining process; counterfeit coinage; the rare 1804 dollar including an article announcing the sale of the late Matthew Stickney’s collection by his daughters, which included the 1804 dollar, to Henry Chapman, Jr. (NY Herald, Jan. 20, 1907); and an article announcing a gift to the Society of Roman coins from the Warren D. Gookin collection (The Sun, Dec. 30, 1906).
  Open to all researchers.
- Series: Manuals, 1914-1974; 1 cubic feet (1 box)
  Manuals (Instructional materials); Correspondence; Reports; Circulars (Fliers); Agendas (Administrative records)
  Originally a set of nine binders containing materials pertaining to ANS policies and procedures, including council meeting extracts, memorandums, letters, lists, and printed matter. Materials have been removed from the binders and placed into folders containing the following: (1) filing of financial records, financial structure, insurance, additions to inventory, security (1964-1968); (2) council extracts pertaining to ANS management, master list of the numbered filing system for ANS records, billing procedures, coin boxes, cash receipts books, code numbers assigned to various numismatic geographical and topical interests, form letters, donor files (1964-1974); (3) constitution and bylaw amendments (1948-1973); (4) meeting agendas, notifications, and summaries, as well as announcements and circulars sent to the membership, which include the Centennial Medal, 1958, and the Louis C. West Medal, 1960 (1950-1972); (5) council meeting schedules, membership lists, an expense trend report, an International Numismatic Congress (INC) list of registrants (1973), bank letter procedures, and financial computations (1971-1973); (6) ANS printed materials and circulars for medals issued from 1914 to 1958 (1914-1959); (7) procedures and rates for photography and casts, cleaning coins, and circulars pertaining to ANS publications (1950-1969); (8) publishing distribution dates, prices, and stock locations (1964-1972); and (9) council resolutions (1940-1967).
  Some materials may be restricted to outside researchers.
    nnan0121/c_78ab75142c0c6913d232d202ad46c490
  - Binder 1: I, 1964-1968
  - Binder 2: II, 1964-1974
  - Binder 3: Amendments, 1948-1973
  - Binder 4: Council notices, etc., 1950-1972
  - Binder 5: Meetings, bank letter procedures, financial computations, 1971-1973
  - Binder 6: Miscellaneous printed forms and medals, 1914-1959
  - Binder 7: Photography and casts, publications, 1950-1969
  - Binder 8: Publications, 1964-1972
  - Binder 9: Resolutions, 1940-1967
- Series: Audio cassette tapes, 1988-2003; 8 audio cassette tapes
  NPR program and Sasanian conference are open to all. ANS council meeting tape is restricted.
  National Public Radio (NPR) Morning Edition Program on U.S. coin design changes, July 27, 1988, hosted by Barbara Mantel, with guests William Bischoff, David Ganz, D. Harper, and D.(onna?) Pope.; ANS council meeting re William Street, June 22, 2002; Sasanian conference, June 2003.